<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable Sir James Edwards, Lord Mayor, in St. Lawrence Church on the feast of St. Michael, 1679, at the election of Sir Robert Clayton to be Lord Mayor for the ensuing year by Greg. Hascard ...</title>
            <author>Hascard, Gregory.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43062</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1114</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12242</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13016569</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13016569</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96553</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43062)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96553)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 741:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable Sir James Edwards, Lord Mayor, in St. Lawrence Church on the feast of St. Michael, 1679, at the election of Sir Robert Clayton to be Lord Mayor for the ensuing year by Greg. Hascard ...</title>
                  <author>Hascard, Gregory.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 29 [i.e. 32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Crooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clayton, Robert, --  Sir, 1629-1707.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96553:1"/>
            <p>Edwards Mayor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cur. ſpecial. tent. die Lune, in Feſto Sancti Michaelis Archangeli,</hi> 1679. <hi>Anno<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Regis Caroli Secundi Angliae,</hi> &amp;c. XXXj<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>THis Court doth deſire Dr. <hi>Haſcard</hi> to Print his SERMON Preached this Morning at St. <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> Church, before the Election of the LORD MAYOR.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WAGSTAFFE.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:96553:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the Right Honourable Sir <hi>JAMES EDWARDS</hi> Lord Mayor, In St. <hi>Lawrence</hi> Church, On the FEAST of St. <hi>Michael,</hi> 1679. AT THE ELECTION OF Sir <hi>ROBERT CLAYTON</hi> TO BE Lord MAYOR for the enſuing Year.</p>
            <p>By GREG. HASCARD D. D. Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majeſty, and Rector of S. <hi>Clements Danes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>William Crooke</hi> at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> without Temple-bar. 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:96553:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96553:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JUDE v. 8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>— Deſpiſe dominions, and ſpeak evil of dignities.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE care and tenderneſs of this Apoſtle over his new-baptized Chriſtians, was the cauſe of this Epiſtle: well fore-ſeeing how theſe young Diſciples (like <hi>Adam</hi> in his firſt Plantation, or <hi>Hercules</hi> in his Cradle by Serpents) would be aſſaulted by men of ſubtle intereſt and ſly deſigns, who would pervert Chriſtianity from its firſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and plain intention of reforming the Minds of Men, and preſcribing them me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods how they ſhould arrive at Immortality; and cauſe it to degenerate onely into ſome wanton purpoſes of licentiouſneſs and paſſion, the little ends of earth and intereſt, and tread upon their Saviours Body for a Temporal ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement. For no ſooner was Chriſtianity planted in the Pagan world, (the buſie ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit below, and his Factors the <hi>Carpocratians</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96553:3"/>here, ſtriving to blaſt Religion in its ſpring) but ſo ſtrange a change appears in all its Doctrines, and the Lives of thoſe Profeſſors too, that you might ſeek Chriſtianity in ſuch a Chriſtian World, and yet ſcarce find it: for as the Apoſtle deſcribes it here, their Faith was changed into fancy and polluting dreams; their unity and peace, into Schiſm and Separation; their Humility and Mortification, into Pride and Luxury; their reſignation and ſedateneſs of mind in all conditions, into mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings and complainings; and all Religion ſo hugely changed, as though it had waſht an <hi>Aethiopian;</hi> or the Pagan World, with all its Vices and Idols too, had onely wheel'd about again to be ador'd in a new Chriſtian dreſs. The apoſtle like a good Centinel ſtanding upon his guard, and diſcovering the approaches of the Enemy, ſounds an Alarm to his true Diſciples, <hi>v.</hi> 3. and bids them <hi>contend earneſtly for the Faith that was once delivered unto the Saints.</hi> And that they might know their Enemies the better, he paints them out in their own colours: that they were men for their wickedneſs ſo lively pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy'd of long before; they are ſaid to be,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96553:3"/>
               <hi>v.</hi> 4. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> paſted up: that they were <hi>ungodly men, who turn'd the grace of God into laſciviouſneſs, and denyed the onely Lord God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> 
               <note n="⋆" place="margin"> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> M. 8.</note> And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the diſmal Examples of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha,</hi> of <hi>Corah</hi> and his Company, <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Balaam,</hi> mentioned <hi>v.</hi> 10, 11. they were reſolute and incorrigible in their ſins, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this more to their former crimes, they ſcorn'd the power and authority which might correct them, and <hi>deſpiſed Dominions, and ſpoke evil of Dignities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Deſpiſing and ſpeaking evil of Dominions and Dignities, is nothing elſe, but by words and actions to diſturb, reſiſt, and defame our Governours. By <hi>Dominions</hi> and <hi>Dignities,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (not Orders of ſpirits above, of which theſe Hereticks told fine ſtories) the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract for the Concrete, is meant, all ſorts of Rulers and Governours, equivalent to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note n="⋆" place="margin">Rom. 13; 1.</note> the <hi>higher Powers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Political Government and Authority being ſo clearly founded by Divine Commands, and ſeconded by the abſolute neceſſity of Humane Nature, with the conſent of all Mankind; it ſeems a Miracle, that among the lowd Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96553:4"/>of this degenerate Age, Diſobedience to Kings and Magiſtrates, contempt of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and Truſtees of power, ſhould be a crying one: As though Men courted Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy and Confuſion, and were in love with ruine and diſorder. Some who will not pay Obedience to any Command that is not clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drawn from Holy Writ, 'tis ſtrange their own principle, though falſe and ſtingy, will yet countenance them in deſpiſing Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is as clear in Sacred Volume, as the Sun in his noon-day glory. The Man of earth, that meaſures all things by profit and deſign, and nothing is juſt and Divine, but what is uſeful and convenient, 'tis a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he ſhould miſtake his rule ſo far, as to caſt dirt upon Dominion and its ſeveral Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, which is the original of all his quiet, and the onely ſecurity of his Temporal Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. However this comes to paſs, yet we ſadly find, that the Ghoſts of theſe <hi>Carpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratians</hi> are come out of their Graves, and haunt the world again; and civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though confirmed by Chriſt, yet like him is crucified between theſe two; Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſts, and Men of Deſigns and Policies; the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96553:4"/>one cries it princheth upon Conſcience, it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trencheth upon Chriſtian Liberty; that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy becomes not a Chriſtian man; it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grades the priviledge of grace to found Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and juſtles with the Almighty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave and Conſiſtory, to whom all Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ought to ſubmit. The Son of <hi>Matchia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel;</hi> that proſtitutes every thing to his poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick devices, the windings of his brain, and private happineſs, declaims aloud againſt the grandeur of Princes; that acts of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy are onely Force and Tyranny, the abridgment of civil Immunities, and natural Liberties; that their Titles are high and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-Chriſtian; that they confound equality of nature, and ſelf-preſervation; that Tribes and Families, with a whole Nation, groan to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Pomp and Retinue of Regal Power, and are onely ſlaves to burthen and greatneſs. Hence inſtead of Honour and Fame, Reward and Duty, that we ought juſtly to pay to our Governours for their care and faithful diſcharge, the onely aſſurance of what we call our own; we put lewd ſences upon their Actions, black cenſures upon their Perſons, Paſquils upon their Place and Authority, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96553:5"/>them all like ſo many Mock-Kings, with a reed for a Scepter, and Laurels about their brow, a phantaſtick guard againſt the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Tongues, with an <hi>Hail King,</hi> firſt to abuſe, and then to crucifie.</p>
            <p>Firtſt, let us conſider from whence this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt doth ſpring. To omit many others, we ſhall onely mention theſe four.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) From a Principle of Vice. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Names of theſe men were, againſt whom the Apoſtle levels this Epiſtle, to be ſure they were <hi>ungodly men,</hi> that abuſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to all manner of Luſt and Paſſion; for ſo the Apoſtle expreſsly tells us, <hi>v.</hi> 4. and the Learned ſay, that this Epiſtle was wrote againſt the <hi>Carpocratians,</hi> a lewd Sect in the early days of Chriſtianity, (as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> and others ſet them out) who, that they might be the more ſecure in their groſſer Luſts, affirm'd that nothing was good or evil in it ſelf, but in opinion; and lookt upon all ſort of Vice, as their natural Freedome and lawful Liberty; <note n="⋆" place="margin">Non mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum id fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſe Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocratia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, qui leges avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas omnes pro nihilo ducerent. <hi>Grot. in Judam, v. 8.</hi>
               </note> and ſcorn'd all Authority; and if the Magiſtrate endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to correct them, his Power muſt be grim'd for Tyranny, and his Authority call'd
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96553:5"/>Uſurpation. 'Tis no wonder the brute acts like himſelf, ſometimes biting the Chain, and ſometimes barking at the Whip that is held for his correction. To the vicious, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate appears an Executioner and <note n="⋆" place="margin">Rom. 13.3.</note> 
               <hi>a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of wrath;</hi> but his Vice drew him in thoſe black colours: But to the good, he is a Guardian-Angel. He that will ſacrifice all to Self-love and Paſſion, and would have all Encloſures pull'd up, <hi>ruat Coelum,</hi> &amp;c. that he might walk up and down like a Beaſt of Luſt and Prey with his lawleſs Paſſion, 'tis no wonder that he grows angry with his Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that bounds him, and ſaith to his froth and madneſs, as Providence to the <hi>Waves,</hi> (<note n="⋆" place="margin">v. 13.</note> ſo theſe are called) <hi>Hitherto ſhall you go; and no further.</hi> Fond and diſſolute men propoſe to themſelves days of Paradiſe, could they but tumble down their Governours, and <hi>break their bonds in ſunder;</hi> yet after a ſurfeit in Vice, and weary with Ruine and Diſorder, they would either ſtep into the Chair them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or beg of ſome more prudent to take the reins; concluding that the rods of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants are milder far than the blinde ſtate of Nature and Confuſion. The Extravagant
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96553:6"/>know very well, that Governours are deſign'd for Champions of Religion and Virtue, the common Patrons of all good Men, the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the bad, and the ſcourge of Vice; and his Love can be but a ſlaviſh Fear at beſt, that they might not hurt him. As Vice doth grow, ſo much is Government con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn'd; while Vice diſcourag'd is Virtues Triumph, and the ſupport of Government. Such ill conceptions have men of Vice, to conclude, there is no Liberty, becauſe there is a Law; and they are in Bondage, becauſe they cannot be Licentious: Whereas good Laws are the ſecurity of our juſt Freedoms and trueſt Intereſt; and he that Governs, and Commands us onely to be happy and truely Men, we ought not to look upon as the Jaylor of our Liberties, the great Retrencher of our Freedoms, to beſpatter and deſpiſe; but our Friend and Benefactor, to admire and love.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) From a ſilly Opinion that all Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is founded in Grace, there was a ſort of Chriſtians who beſtow'd upon themſelves alone the fine names of <hi>Elect</hi> and <hi>Gracious;</hi> and upon this title challeng'd Empire; and all Governours not ſo qualified, they cry'd
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96553:6"/>down for Tyrants and Uſurpers: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by Grace they expected Heaven, they thought themſelves the only fit perſons to govern Earth. Point-blank againſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Kingdome and Spiritual Deſigne of Chriſt: For if upon the ſcore of Saintſhip a Right to rule the world is derived, our Saviour's Kingdome (notwithſtanding his declaration before <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi>) is of this world, by a new Title which he brought down with him. And if you be once a <hi>ſound believer,</hi> and <hi>a ſincere convert</hi> to the Chriſtian Faith, you have a better Title to a Scepter, than Succeſſion, or Election, or any Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral right can give; and to be Orthodox, is a nearer ſtep to a Throne, than Birth, and all the Voices of a Nation: A way to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment unknown to the world before, and is onely a new priviledge of Chriſt's Subjects, to be Chriſtians that they might be Kings; and the liberty of his Religion ſhould free Servants and Sons, and other Relatives, from Duty and Obedience. Theſe are the men indeed that have turn'd the world and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion upſide down: which Chriſt gave to Mankind to reform their manners,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96553:7"/>and to ſave them; to confirm good orders and rules, and leave the world to the freedom of civil rights and conveyances as he found them; which are plain and viſible, and fall under a ſenſible cogniſance; but whoſe Grace is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine and true, may not be known till this world with all its principalities and powers ſhall be no more. As though Chriſtianity came to procure rewards for Hypocrites, who by their gay pretences, and gilded zeal, can impoſe upon the leſs-diſcerning world; and his ſeeming Piety, join'd with ill-nature, and impudence to call all above him Reprobates, muſt be made the moſt ſpecious right unto an Empire: and becauſe what is onely fancy and fondneſs, paſſion and effeminacy, whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey and Enthuſiaſin, is call'd by the name of Grace; all theſe will ſet up their Standards for the Empire too, and lay all the blood and confuſion following from theſe ſeveral Titles at the door of Grace. And becauſe the world hath torn in pieces and confounded Chriſtianity, and call'd their own Faction and profit Fundamentals in Chriſt's Kingdom, and ſplit it into numerous parties and diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and each confines Chriſt and all his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96553:7"/>to themſelves, and they are the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gracious perſons, and will be ſav'd; they have confounded Temporal Government; all theſe different perſwaſions pretending to rule, becauſe their Chriſt and Grace are true, and all beſides are falſe. Poor <hi>Wicliff</hi> was condemned by a Popiſh Council, <note n="⋆" place="margin">Concil. Tom. <hi>12.</hi> p. <hi>46.</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. <hi>15.</hi> Nullus eſt Dominus civilis, nullus eſt Paraelatus, nullus eſt Epiſcopus, dum eſt in peccato mortali.</note> that of <hi>Conſtants,</hi> and one of his criminal perſwaſions was this, that <hi>Dominion was founded in grace.</hi> But the Pope his Judge hath baptized himſelf into the Hereſie of his Malefactor, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on account of Chriſtian Religion and Grace committed to him to manage, ought to be the onely Univerſal Monarch. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the deſign of Chriſtianity was to take men off from earth, and make this world onely a ſtep to another State; this is the way to make men earthly and ſenſual, and to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious onely becauſe ambitious and proud, to ſway the world by this new Title, which (they ſay) Chriſt gave, to be as bountiful to Chriſtians, as ever <hi>Mahomet</hi> to his Diſciples. Religion, that fixes the Crowns of Kings faſter upon their Heads, by theſe deſigning men muſt be wreſted to diſturb the peace of Kingdoms, and to ſettle licentiouſneſs, or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96553:8"/>freedome from Temporal Laws, by a preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Spiritual one, That onely Saints have a right to rule and poſſeſs the Earth. This makes Chriſtianity but a quaint device, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert mens eyes and affections from earth, that they might have the fairer opportunity to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it. Theſe men in effect ſay, their Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our was too modeſt in refuſing to be Crown'd a King; <note n="⋆" place="margin">2 Kings 5.20.</note> and like <hi>Gehazi,</hi> when his Maſter had refus'd the Preſent, run after and cry, he denyed his own rights, and if he will not, yet they, purely upon account of ſecret cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of Spirit and Grace, ought to be heads of Dominion, and rule the World. This ſtops the conqueſt of Religion, when the Pagan King muſt change his Religion, and may looſe his Diadem whenever Baptiz'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of others that may be elder and better Saints the he: for who knows where ſuch freaks will end? Had this been a genuine Doctrine of Chriſtianity in the firſt times, it had certainly been confin'd to a narrower compaſs than now 'tis in: but as Kings and Governours became its nurſing Fathers, did, and juſtly might out of gratitude expect more reverence and duty, and not contempt upon their dignities and perſons.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96553:8"/>
            <p n="3">3. Contempt of Government ſprings from that lewd opinion, That Dominion is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but ſtrength and might. That Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy that reſolves all beings and actions into matter and motion, lays the foundation too of all Obedience not Conſcience and Divine Commands, but the ſtrongeſt arm and longeſt Sword; onely Subjects, becauſe they are over-power'd. What doth vilifie our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours more than this principle? whom we beautified before with the Titles of Sacred and Divine, but now are made onely a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon lump of ſtrength and power; and are really weaker, becauſe their Subjects too, like them, are onely Arms, but no Heart or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, no internal principle to oblige unto Obedience. For if no inward perſwaſion and dread of an Higher Power, but onely fear and intereſt, weakneſs and convenience, are the bottom and reaſon of our Obedience; when theſe ſhall change, and the man hath ſwell'd his Coffers, procur'd firm Alliances, and muſter'd up his Armies and Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, and other inſtruments of Rebellion; he may then, by the Title of Power, lay claim to Dominion, and call himſelf a Prince. Thus
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96553:9"/>the Lyon and the Eagle are two Kings, the one of Beaſts, and the other of Birds, becauſe of the longeſt paw, and the ſharpeſt pounces. For duty for want of power, is onely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion demurr'd, and waits only its proper ſeaſon to bring forth, and ſet up for himſelf: for ſelf-love is the ſtingy principle of all his actions: what ſignifies Religious Oaths, and ſolemn Vows to engage us unto Obedience, which is onely an acknowledgment of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, if onely external power muſt be their keeper? This makes a Chriſtian Government the rule of Brutes and Infidels, where one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rage and fury, Tyranny and Oppreſſion, and <hi>Solomons</hi> Lyons, the Supporters of his Throne, ſit in it. And 'tis contempt upon the Governour, that his Subjects are ſo, not out of Conſcience and Religion, as becomes Men and Chriſtians; but out of a ſordid principle of fear and weakneſs, as becomes Brutes or Vaſſals.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This contempt upon Government, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from an Atheiſtical principle. When once the debauched world hath put out the fires below, and torn in pieces the Account-Books of the laſt Bar, and diſ-thron'd a God
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96553:9"/>above, they will look upon his Deputies as Phantaſtick Creatures, becauſe intituled with the ſame name, and are called <hi>Gods.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſalm 82.6.</note> 'Tis no wonder, when men look upon the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection like the ſowing of <hi>Cadmus</hi> his Teeth, a Poetical Fable, and laugh at or deſpair of a future ſtate of happineſs, that they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage this life to the beſt advantage; and to ſerve their pleaſure or intereſt, break all the tyes of Honour and Duty, which they look upon as terms of Art or Trade, or Dreams and Fancies of Religious heads; which will confound all order and ſecurity of Mankind, and the world ſhall have nothing more of the ſcales of Juſtice in it, than that the one goes up, and the other down, oppreſt by greater Power and flyer Intereſt. The Atheiſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys that which fitly qualifies Subjects to be truely ſo: are they expected to be ſtout and daring? What will ſooner make them ſo, than to perſwade them they ſhall ſurvive their body, and wear a Crown? For he onely fears to dye, who knows not how to live, nor what betides him afterwards; and Vice or Infidelity makes in a Coward. Is a faithful ſecrecy, frugality, thriftineſs, ſobriety, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96553:10"/>temperance, care and diligence, lookt upon as the perfection of a people? Theſe are the commands and genuine iſſues of a Religious life. And Patience and Humility, Obedience and Honour to Superiours, are great and indiſpenſable Duties in Religion. So that while the man of Wit and Atheiſm beſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Religion, he caſts dirt upon Authority. 'Twas the wiſdom and goodneſs of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Law-giver, to twiſt our Temporal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, with our eternal happineſs; that when Princes ſhould embrace the Chriſtian Religion, and become its nurſing Fathers, the belief of Immortality ſhould beger more obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Sons and Loyal Subjects. Could we ſuppoſe the Prince to lay aſide his Sword and other methods of Government, and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly like a Philoſopher, treat his Subjects by arguments; the firm belief of Immortality alone, would be ſufficient to command obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; it being againſt the common ſenſe of Humane Nature, to be perſwaded of the greateſt good, Immortality, yet not to have an influence upon his mind to guard his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and therefore dares not deſpiſe Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, leſt he forfeits that which he moſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96553:10"/>deſires: for Religion hath been ſo careful to ſupport the Secular arm, as to lay double tyes, like St. <hi>Pauls</hi> bonds, to oblige the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto Obedience; allowing all earthly power; but to make it invincible, hath added the dread of an omnipotent arm. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that buffoons with Religion, is rude with Majeſty, and is prophane, and a Rebel too, at the ſame time; and wounds the Authority of Princes, laughing at the mighty argument of Conſcience and Immortality, as much as ever <hi>Clement</hi> or <hi>Ravilliac</hi> did their perſons. Vows of Obedience, and Oaths of Fidelity, would be onely the labour of Lips and Lungs, and like common air, for convenience taken in, and for the ſame ſent out gain; having no other fear upon him, but leſt his Perjury and Treaſon ſhould become publick and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſsful. This is the mighty intereſt by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; Princes grow ſtronger, and Subjects ſafer; that Obedience ſhall not be ſowr'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Slavery, nor Liberty ſwell into Rebellion; the loſs of Immortality, which the Atheiſt laughs at, and in that at Government, being at the ſtake for Prince and people too.</p>
            <p>Let us in the next place conſider what
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96553:11"/>are the obligations to Duty and Honour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Governours: we ſhall briefly urge onely two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us conſider what eſteem God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to beſtow upon them; which are not purely <note n="⋆" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Humane Creatures, made onely for, and by a mutable conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but indiſpenſable, by reaſon of mens neceſſities and imperfections, and created by God. For though variety of Governments are left to men when free to chooſe, and are various according to the Intereſts and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries in which they dwell; yet being once well eſtabliſht, the poſſeſſors of them are Gods Vice-Gerents, they repreſent his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Authority, and by him Kings Reign; and in this ſence, <note place="margin">Prov. 8.15, 16.</note> ⋆ all other Governments, as well as that of the Jews, are Theocratical, and have God for their Supreme, and muſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwer unto him. They are array'd with ſuch Titles as will command more reverence than all their Purples and Enſigns of Honour, being call'd the Deputies of God, <note place="margin">Pſ. 82.6.2. Chron. 6.42. Deut. 1.17.1 Sam. 15.23.</note> and adopt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into his Family; entituled by the ſame name, and called Gods: their Inauguration is ſolemn and grave, all circumſtances are high and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96553:11"/>and are ſtiled <hi>God's Anointed:</hi> their judgment and deciſions are God's: Rebellion is branded by the name of Witchcraft, an Apoſtacy from God or his Authority; and an eternal doom for its reward, <note n="⋆" place="margin">Rom. 13.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall receive to themſelves damnation.</hi> When we deſpiſe Dominion therefore, we ſpit at Heaven, and appear in Hoſtility and fight againſt God; and as much as in us lies, like unconverted <hi>Saul,</hi> we perſecute him, and the blow toucheth his Throne; and for as much as we do it to one of his Governours, as well as Saints, we do it unto him: yet to keep them humble, they muſt <hi>dye like men;</hi> and to guard their actions, they muſt be reſponſible at an high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Bar; and by reaſon of their Male-Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, have the Crimes of Cities and Countries laid unto their charge; and the puniſhment is as great to the bad, as rewards to the good. And St. <hi>Peter,</hi> to ſtrike an awe upon mens minds towards their Governours, tells them, 'twas the aggravation of theſe <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocratians,</hi> and their followers Crime, <note n="⋆" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. 2 Pet. 2.10.</note> That they were <hi>bold and contumacious men, and did not tremble when they blaſphemed Dignities:</hi> And this Apoſtle, to ſet them an excellent
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96553:12"/>Preſident of Honour and Reſpect to Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, tells them, that when the mighty Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angel <hi>Michael,</hi> (whoſe Feaſt the Church this day celebrates) <hi>when contending with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and diſputing about the body of</hi> Moſes, <note place="margin"> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> v. 9.</note> 
               <hi>would not give him any contumelious words,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had ſome power given him, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by God, and was the Prince of the air, or god of this World.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us conſider what benefit we receive by them: if eaſe and quiet, property and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, be the mighty bleſſings of the world, we owe this to the Magiſtrates care and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution in the execution of Laws, without which, they would be but imaginary guards and formality. For ſuch are the degenerate minds of men, that the natural love of God and Virtue, and the Laws of Chriſtianity (though very apt and fit in themſelves) have not that force as gently to perſwade men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Duty and Obedience; but Swords of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Temporal puniſhment muſt keep the world in awe: and what a ſtrange mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter this world would be, if either no Laws, no Pale of Government was ſet; or elſe for want of guards and keepers, every man
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96553:12"/>might pluck up or leap over at pleaſure! it would be but a ſecond Chaos, or greater Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, like the ſtate of the wild <hi>Arabs,</hi> or the <hi>Banditi;</hi> and every one would prey upon his fellow-being. So that the Magiſtrate gives life to the dead letter of the Law, and in that gives the ſhadow and fruit to our Vines, Titles to our Poſſeſſions, ſecurity to our Lives, and is the Caſtle againſt our fears and jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. Which calls for, inſtead of Contempt and Scorn, the higheſt Eſteem and Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, from theſe things conſider'd, let us here lay a particular Charge againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> who doth moſt eminently <hi>deſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeak evil of Dignities;</hi> who challengeth a right not onely to Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, Depoſe, and Kill the Perſons of Princes, and Abſolve their Subjects from their Duty and Allegiance, but allows her Champions to rail at, and vilifie the Perſons and Powers of Princes, in a moſt ignominious way, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will not pay an abſolute Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſubmit their Authority to hers: the conſtitution of that Church being to put down all Authority and Power, to Rival
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96553:13"/>Kings, to advance her Prieſthood, and make her Biſhop a Mighty Prince; who (they ſay) like his Lord, is inveſted with all Power both in Heaven and in Earth, and is conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted to root up, and to plant; to put on, and kick off the Crowns of Princes; to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of their Royalties and Dominions; to tread upon their Necks, and laſh their Backs; to proclaim their Wars, and conclude their Peace; to contract or diſſolve their Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; to preſs the Prince and the People to Holy Wars, or his private Quarrels; to play the Herald, and give mighty Titles, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Precedencies; to Levy Texas, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt his Clergy; to interdict a Land, and legitimate Rebellion, and ſpurious Children; to diſpatch or <hi>bind their Kings in chains, and their Nobles in fetters of Iron;</hi> in plain, to ſhew a great deal of Pride and earthlineſs, diſguiſed by Spiritual Names and Titles, to advance the Kingdom of Chriſt, which he hathh made as Temporal as any. For though his Maſter Jeſus was humble and mortifi'd, and refuſed and Earthly Kingdom offered to him by the Devil and the Jews; yet this fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal ſervant of his tells him, he underſtood
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96553:13"/>not his own Merit and Title, and he ought to look after his Maſters Rights, and not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the donation of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and the bounty of Princes, and ſuch low Titles; but from a power deriv'd to him from that Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Monarch, King Jeſus, muſt govern Chriſtendom. Chriſtendom. Chriſt told indeed <hi>Pontius Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> the Procurator of <hi>Judea,</hi> that <hi>his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was not of this world;</hi> but he had a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent reſervation in the caſe, ſo as not to tell them, becauſe they could not bear it then, and make good uſe of it; his Religion was but in its Non-age or Minority, but his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor ſhould come and lead them into this mighty Truth, diſplay his Banner, and tell the World and its petty Princes, that now the Kingdom of God and his Chriſt was come with power. In thoſe early days of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, Loyalty and Obedience were mightly Duties to Temporal Princes; but then Chriſtian were few and weak, (to this purpoſe their two Cardinals <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Allen</hi> have ſpoke:) but the caſe is alter'd, they are now more numerous and ſtrong; and the time is come, when the fifth Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, ſurpaſſing the <hi>Graecian</hi> and others, muſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96553:14"/>be ſet up at <hi>Rome.</hi> Bleſſed Jeſus! when thou told'ſt the Judge and the Jews this truth, thou didſt it with the greateſt ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, in the plaineſt terms, <note n="⋆" place="margin">John 18. 36.</note> that <hi>thy Kingdom was not of this World,</hi> and would not claſh with Secular Princes; and this was thy open will and pleaſure: but thy Infallible Vicar tells us of a ſecret will, and private Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons given to thy Apoſtles, thy Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, and thy Succeſſor, that when all things were ripe, and the World better Diſciplin'd and Tutor'd, they ſhould ſet forth their Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and write over the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Head, <hi>This is the mighty King of the Chriſtians;</hi> and make the ſturdy Monarchs ſubmit their Necks unto him, by kiſſing his feet, holding his ſtirrup, waiting at his Gates, and other ſlaviſh acknowledgments. For when he pretends to all the fore-mentioned power, what is it but to be the onely Abſolute Monarch on Earth, though he wears the Robes of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World? For the humble and Spiritual Names of Biſhop and Paſtor, Servant of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Silver and Gold have I none, the Seal of the Fiſherman in Lead, and the like, turn all into Scene and Laughter, when they are
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96553:14"/>contradicted by the ſwelling Titles that their flattering Canoniſts and others beſtow upon him; as, <note n="⋆" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Fowlis <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> p. 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 36, 37, 38.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord our God;</hi> that he is <hi>far above all Principalities and Powers,</hi> that <hi>every knee muſt bow to him both in Heaven and in Earth;</hi> that <hi>he is</hi> Moſes <hi>by Authority,</hi> Peter <hi>by Power, and Chriſt by Vnction:</hi> that he is <hi>Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtar of Juſtice, Arbitrator of all things, Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of Chriſtians, and Image of Divinity:</hi> that <hi>he can diſpenſe with Laws, and againſt the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle:</hi> that <hi>he is Spouſe of the Vniverſal Church, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords:</hi> that <hi>a prieſt excels a King, as much as a man doth a Brute:</hi> that <hi>a Prieſt is as much better than a King, as God is better than a Prieſt:</hi> and they are commanded to bow at the name of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> and the Pope, as well as at the Name of Jeſus. Theſe and many more are the <hi>great ſwelling words</hi> which theſe <hi>Carpocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> vented, <hi>v.</hi> 16. far beyond what ever the <hi>Aſiatick</hi> Princes in their greateſt Luxury and Pride did ever affect. Is not this plainly to tell the world, that Conſcience is intereſt, the Altar is the Exchequer, the Church and Court are the ſame, and Chriſtianity new policy contrived by Chriſt, and communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96553:15"/>to St. <hi>Peter</hi> and his Succeſſor? Their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſts, with their nice Diſtinctions, can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch the minds of men into Treaſon and Murder, Lying and Hypocriſie, and the lewdeſt Vices; yet can paſs uncerſur'd, and ſometimes rewarded: yet queſtion but his power and juriſdiction, which he calls <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Faith,</hi> the ſevereſt penalty in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſtion may be your doom. And therefore very bountifully &amp; wiſely he hath ſometimes yielded ſome Articles of his Faith, as the half Communion and the like, upon condition they would admit of his Power and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; as though the ſole deſign of Chriſts coming into this world, was to lay down new methods of Government; to be a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican himſelf (as well as eat with them) and gather <hi>Peters</hi> pence, onely to be rich and great. Though ſome of <hi>Romes</hi> Champions are more modeſt, and aſſume this power onely indirectly, <hi>in ordine ad ſpiritualia,</hi> to ſerve Religion; yet others more bare-fac'd, challenge a direct power over Princes, their Territories, places of Truſt, and all their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galities: yet the other is very comprehenſive, and can at pleaſure throw off the Mask, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96553:15"/>face to face tell the Sovereign, that all his power in ſending Embaſſadors, in ſtriking Leagues, in making his Miniſters, and other Actions of State, muſt now be devolved on him, for the well-being of Chriſtianity: and the Prince hath little benefit by it, that he is kill'd by St. <hi>Peters</hi> Keys knockt about his cars, and not his Sword. And ſuch Canons and Conſtitutions, whatever the gilded name and Conſtitutions, whatever the gilded name and pretence is, are as much of this world, as the Edicts and Acts of Princes. And whereas the Diſciples of Chriſt were <hi>firſt called Chriſtians at</hi> Antioch, they were firſt call'd <hi>Matchiavilians</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> the Seat of this new Chriſtian Empire.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let this re-mind the Magiſtrate of a faithful diſcharge, and our ſelves of Duty and Honour towards him; and what more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Arguments to do this, than to bid him conſider, who it is he repreſents; what. bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings he procures to Mankind, and how he ſerves himſelf with infinite rewards, and a publick Character of a good Servant, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of his Maſters joy? This is the beſt way to ſilence ſcurrilous tongues, to be as good in Life, as high in Dignity: for an eminent
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96553:16"/>vertue and clear uprightneſs lays violence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mens judgments, and will puſh forward a juſt Character of a faithful Ruler. But if this fail, yet however, like the <hi>Roman</hi> Senators when the <hi>Barbarians</hi> ſhould enter <hi>Rome,</hi> they put on their Senatorian Robes, <hi>&amp; Curulibus ſellis ſeſe poſuerunt, ut cum veniſſet hoſtis in ſuà dignitate morerentur;</hi> and plac't themſelves in their Chairs, that if this ſight would not procure reſpect, yet like men of honour and juſtice, at leaſt they might dye in their Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities. This is the deſign of all the powers and abilities that nature hath enricht men withal, to ſerve their fellow-beings, and make an univerſal ſpirit for the good of all mankind. He that reacheth at dignity, the better onely to drive on ſome petty pleaſure, or ſuck in vulgar air; acts like <hi>Domitian,</hi> makes it an Empire to hunt and kill a fly. He that courts Power onely for an opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to return ſome injuries, and ſerve his ſpleon, doth blaſphemouſly praiſe the Deity, whoſe Deputy he is, that he hath given him an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion like a monſter of nature only to poiſon and kill. He that begs the place onely for the ſplendour of it, like young <hi>Phaëton—Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96553:16"/>miratur habenas,</hi> admiring the gilded reins of Government, yet putting the world on fire; of ſerves only his private intereſt, and like a dark Lanthorn, only ſhines to himſelf; abuſeth his mighty Office, heightens his own account, to be call'd a god, and do leſs than man. But to the good Governours our eſteem ought to be as high as their places are; not weighing their worth by rigorous propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but charitable allowances for the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances they are in: 'tis but a common grace we owe to the errors of all Mankind; but a more peculiar debt of Charity we owe to our Superiours, whoſe ways of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation and place, expoſe them to keener temptations, and more fierce aſſaults, which may make them yield ſometimes. But inſtead of prudent concealment, and caſting in the grains of charity and favourable Comments upon the Lives and Actions of our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, we ſwell indifferent actions into er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, every ſlip and infirmity we grime for a mortal ſin, and ſingle ſins we change into habits; and theſe muſt needs pull down the perſon and his dignity too. As though that Head had onely right to wear a Crown,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96553:17"/>whoſe Life was as clear as the Jewels of it; or as though he might not be an ill man, and yet a good Governour; or that Principalities, like Eſtates of Ideots for want of Wit, could be begg'd for want of Grace. We ſcan the words and actions of our Superiours; we anatomize their thoughts and deſigns; and the ſpots of their Lives, like thoſe of the Moon, by the glaſſes of our cenſorious fancies, we ſwell into Mountains, to ſerve our reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, our party, or our ſpleen; repreſenting <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> that Prince of flies, that feaſts on ſores, and is pleas'd with the errors and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities of men. Such men are uncertain too, dealing with their Rulers as the rabble with <hi>Sejanus,</hi> or the <hi>Barbarians</hi> with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> with their curſes and their flatteries, making no middle between a Murderer and a god: far unlike that firſt Chriſtian Emperour, who would diſ-robe himſelf, to cover the errors of a Spiritual Father.</p>
            <p>And now what can I recommend more ſeaſonably, that unity among your ſelves, to ſerve the ends of your Choice and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and Religion too? Diviſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the antient <hi>Germans</hi> gave an eaſie
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96553:17"/>Victory to the <hi>Roman</hi> Army: <hi>Dum ſinguli pugnant, vincuntur omnes.</hi> Our Enemies grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Policy is, to divide us: let not us execute our Enemies Councels, and be fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves, about the Bells and Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granats of the Temple, when others are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining the very Foundation; or about the fringes of our Garments, when the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Dagger is at our breſts. Common dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ought to unite us,—<hi>jam Caeſar mitte ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes:</hi> When the Stags are fighting among themſelves, it may be kindneſs in <hi>Caeſar</hi> to throw off his dogs upon them. Providence many times makes a Forreign Enemy to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, to reconcile diſcords at home: and now the <hi>Roman</hi> Eagle is upon the wing, the ſeparated chickens ought to run back to the wing of their Mother-Church. 'Twas ſaid: of the two brave <hi>Athenians, Themiſtocles</hi> and <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> that though they had great miſ-underſtanding at home, yet when they went upon any Forreign Expedition, or Warlike deſign for their Countrey, <hi>inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citiam it finibus patriae depoſuerunt,</hi> they left their private quarrels behind them. This would be the way to ſecure King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96553:18"/>Church and State, Religion and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty; that ſitting ſafely with our Lives and Liberties under our own Vines, we might merrily ſing our praiſes to the Lamb, and him that ſits upon the Throne; aſcribing all Power, Might, Majeſty, and Dominion, both now and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
